翻译@守望电影 请保留译者信息
请勿用于商业用途，欢迎关注微博
- Ñandú意思是... - 蜘蛛
- Ñandú means... - Spider.
káva的意思是...黄蜂
And káva means...wasp.
偷窥狂！
Voyeur!
玛伦巴
Malemba,
偷窥狂是谁？
who's the voyeur?
偷窥狂！
Voyeur!
我们需要那个男孩供认
We need the boy to confess.
而且你得找个方法去驳回所有指控
And that you find a way to dismiss all the charges.
他不开口
He's not talking.
要想摆脱自己的处境，首先必须得照顾好它
To free oneself of one's position, one must first take care of it.
我是为了你和这的其他人才说的这些
I say this for you and everyone else here.
他什么也不肯说
He won't talk.
- 让我来可以吗？ - 请便
- May I? - Please.
早上好
Good morning.
文图拉·普列托，治安法官助理
Ventura Prieto, assistant to the magistrate.
你可以走了
You can go.
不会有惩罚的
There will be no punishment.
没有惩罚
No punishment.
你可以离开了
You can go.
但声明还是要有的
Not without a statement.
警卫
Guard,
带他出去
show this good man the way out.
有种鱼...
There's a fish...
有...有种鱼...
There's... a fish...
你宣过誓的
You're still under oath.
有一种鱼
There's a fish
花了一辈子的时间
that spends its life
游来游去
swimming to and fro.
与水斗争，以免被扔到干燥的陆地上
Fighting water that seeks to cast it upon dry land.
因为水排斥它
Because the water rejects it.
水不想要它
The water doesn't want it.
扎马
这些长期受苦的鱼
These long-suffering fish,
依附于排斥它们的元素
so attached to the element that repels them,
它们花费了所有的精力
devote all their energies
只为了留在原地
to remaining in place.
你永远不会在河中央找到它们
You'll never find them in the central part of the river,
但总能在岸边找到
but always near the banks.
费尔南德斯
Fernández.
“我的夫人，我的马尔塔
"My lady, my Marta,
我十分关切地给你写信
I write to you with concern.
14个月来，我一直在等待你和我的孩子们的消息”
For 14 months, I've waited for news of you and my children."
总督告诉我
The Governor told me
不久后我就要离开了
it won't be long before my departure.
总督向我保证
The Governor assured me
不久后我就要离开了
it won't be long before my departure.
有什么可以帮你的？
What do you want?
- 给迭戈·德·扎马的消息 - 我就是
- Message for Diego de Zama. - That's me.
他们在逍遥海滩等你
They're expecting you at Getaway Beach.
- 谁在等我？ - 一个男的
- Who's expecting me? - A man.
我需要你和部长谈谈，迭戈
I need you to speak to the Minister, Diego.
我不想让那些寄生虫上我的船
I don't want those leeches embarking my ship.
你和财政部长的关系好吗？
Your relationship with the Treasury Minister is good?
这里的每个人都愿意做交易，因达莱西奥
Everyone here is willing to do business, Indalecio.
可已经超过一年没有付款了
No payments for over a year.
我们得把奥连特尔人的白兰地卸下来
We have to unload the Oriental's brandy.
他在蒙得维的亚发了财
He's made a fortune in Montevideo.
现在他想扩大自己的业务
Now he wants to expand his business upriver.
马尔塔替我给你写信了吗？
Did Marta give you a letter for me?
马尔塔做出了很多牺牲，迭戈
Marta is making many sacrifices, Diego.
照顾你的孩子
Taking care of your children.
他们在长大
They're growing.
你经常见到她吗？
Did you see her... often?
我的朋友，奥连特尔人！
My friend, the Oriental!
一个从蒙得维的亚看到未来的人！
A man who has seen the future from Montevideo!
我很感激你愿意帮助我们，迭戈先生
I'm grateful that you're willing to help us, don Diego.
请原谅，我现在想去休息一下
If you excuse me, I'll now retire to rest.
我们需要卫队吗？
Do we need an armed escort?
- 他们叫我们小心“维库尼亚” - 维库尼亚已经死了！
- They warned us about a "Vicuña." - Vicuña is dead!
他被杀了有上千次了
He was killed 1000 times.
别担心，你现在在可靠的人手里
Don't worry. You're in good hands now.
去休息吧
Go and rest.
奥连特尔人的儿子
The Oriental's son.
在航海过程中，我告诉过他谁是迭戈·德·扎马先生
During the voyage, I told him who don Diego de Zama was.
治安法官迭戈·德·扎马先生
The magistrate don Diego de Zama.
一个生来
A god who was born old
就不能死的神
and can't die.
他的孤独是残暴的
His loneliness is atrocious.
你在跟我说话吗？
Are you talking to me?
迭戈·德·扎马先生
Don Diego de Zama,
他的管理
vigorous,
非常有力
in charge.
是印第安人的安抚奶嘴，无需拔剑就能伸张正义的人
The pacifier of Indians. He who did justice without drawing his sword.
没有意外或风险，扎马是不会隐藏他的义务
It's not Zama who hides behind obligations without surprises or risks.
“行政首长”扎马，一个具有正义精神的人
Zama the "corregidor". A corregidor with the spirit of justice.
一名执法者
A man of law.
一名法官
A judge.
一个无畏的人
A man without fear.
晚上好
Good evening.
你的衬衣？
Your shirt?
这没其他人，迭戈先生
There's no one, don Diego.
丽塔
Rita.
你受伤了吗？
Are you hurt?
别害怕
There's nothing to fear.
什么人？
Who goes there?
发生了什么？
What's happening?
他们抢了你吗？迭戈先生
Did they rob you, don Diego?
- 是发生抢劫案了吗？ - 没有，我来的正是时候
- Was there a robbery? - No, I arrived just in time.
是那个死去的男孩
It's the dead boy.
是那个皮肤白皙的男孩吗？
Was it a fair-skinned boy?
不，也许吧，我在现场
No. Maybe. I was here.
迭戈...
Diego...
我担心我的女儿们
I fear for my daughters.
她们是我的珍宝
They're my treasure,
高尚的女性
magnificent women.
自从我妻子去世后，我每天晚上都都给她们梳头
Every night since my wife died, I brush their hair.
我为她们担心
I fear for them.
有时候，我醒来
Sometimes, I get up.
去她们的房间
I go to their rooms,
我修理蚊帐，关上窗户...
I fix the mosquito nets, I close the windows...
维库尼亚和他的手下破门而入
Vicuña and his men break into houses
他们过着强奸女人的日子
and pass their days raping women.
他明天会回来的...
He will return tomorrow...
迭戈
Diego,
我担心我的女儿们
I fear for my daughters.
维库尼亚和他的手下破门而入
Vicuña and his men break into houses
他们过着强奸女人的日子
and spend days raping women.
维库尼亚已经被处决了
Vicuña has been executed.
无需再担惊受怕
There's nothing to fear.
他说他明晚会回来的
He said he will return tomorrow night.
迭戈·德·扎马先生！
Don Diego de Zama!
坐这
Sit here.
文图拉·普列托先生！
Don Ventura Prieto!
女士们...
Ladies...
卢西亚娜·皮纳尔·德·卢根加女士！
Doña Luciana Piñares de Luenga!
帮帮我，这件衣服有点不合身
Help me with this, it's poorly fitted.
这里有点紧
It's tight here.
午安
Good afternoon.
混血儿都在这
The mulattas are here.
你不自己动手吗，迭戈先生？
Won't you help yourself, don Diego?
不
No.
你更喜欢白人女孩
You prefer white girls.
是的
Yes.
你这偏好令我很是惊讶
You amaze me with such an exclusive preference.
你在客栈被抢了吗？？
Were you robbed at the inn?
他们抢了你吗？
Did they rob you?
- 有吗？ - 没有，我阻挠了
- Did they? - No, I intervened.
- 是些什么人？ - 我不知道
- Who was it? - I don't know.
昨晚你的房间好像发生了一场混战？
Seems there was a scuffle in your room last night?
他们伤到你了吗？
Did they hurt you?
你房东的女儿刚刚在市场上，她对维库尼亚·波尔图感到非常紧张
Your landlord's daughter was at the market. She was very nervous about Vicuña Porto.
看来迭戈先生得面对维库尼亚了！
It appears Don Diego faced Vicuña!
你奥连特尔的朋友，他可能得了霍乱
Your friend the Oriental, he might have cholera.
还有其他病例
There've been other cases.
- 要我派人去请帕洛斯医生吗？ - 不用了，我早知道会这样了
- Should I send for Doctor Palos? - No, I'm already aware.
为了表彰卢西亚娜·皮纳尔·德·卢根加夫人的客人们
To honor the visit of Señora Luciana Piñares de Luenga,
我们亲爱的卢西亚娜
our beloved Luciana,
她会把彩带递给获胜者
she'll hand out the ribbons to the winner.
我们到美术馆去吧，你可以坐在任何你感觉最自在的地方
Let's head to the gallery. You can sit wherever you feel most at ease.
在我看来，我更喜欢一个忠实可靠
In my case, I prefer the company of a man who bears the white man's burden
纯洁成圣的人
and is sanctified by purity.
卢西亚娜是财政部长的妻子，是吗？
Luciana is the Treasury Minister's wife, right?
是的
Yes.
有个笑话一直在流传
A joke has been making the rounds.
他们说卢西亚娜拥有扎马所想象过的最美的身体
They say Luciana has the most beautiful body that Zama has ever imagined.
谁说的？
Who said that?
大家都这么说
Over there.
秃头人
The bald man.
也许我该走了
Maybe I should leave.
我没有那种气魄
I don't have the strength.
帕洛斯医生？
Doctor Palos?
- 帕洛斯医生？ - 是那个死去的男孩
- Doctor Palos? - It's the dead boy.
那个小圣徒在那儿
The little saint is there.
帕洛斯？
Palos?
你是谁？
Who are you?
我想与财政部长荷奴里奥·皮纳尔·德·卢根加先生谈谈
I wish to speak with the Minister of the Treasury, Señor Honorio Piñares de Luenga.
我的生意可以再说
My business can be postponed.
我需要见一位有荣誉头衔的医生
I need to see a doctor who honors that title.
我可以和房子里的其他人说句话吗？
May I speak with someone in the house?
皮纳尔·德·卢根加夫人，她在里面吗？
And Señora Piñares de Luenga, is she in?
在两个蒸馏器中蒸馏
Distilled in a double alambic.
所以它在准备好之前被蒸馏了很多次
So it's distilled many times before it's ready.
你会很喜欢的
You'll appreciate it.
这些菜谱被谨慎地保护着
These recipes are jealously guarded.
- 你去过布宜诺斯艾利斯吗？ - 去过
- Have you been to Buenos Aires? - Yes.
我读到过许多喜剧剧团和他们的管弦乐队都在那一起演出
I read that many comedy troupes put on plays with their orchestras.
我们这里几乎没有优雅的场所
We have almost no occasion for elegance here.
但你并不缺少优雅
That's not something you lack.
我的妻子想要去那
My wife wanted to go.
而我呢，总是在河上...
Me, I'm always on the river...
来来往往...
that comes and goes...
总是有各种原因到很远的地方去
Always far away, for one reason or another.
它在桶中有些年头了
It's aged in casks.
酒中贵族啊！
Such nobility!
看见那些了吗？
See those?
把小玻璃杯给我
Bring me the little glasses.
不是，较小的那个
No, the smaller ones.
真美
How beautiful.
它们共有十二个，只有八个安全抵达
There were twelve of them. Only eight arrived.
它们被放进了保护得很好的盒子里，但不是所有的盒子都有很好的被包装
They came in a box, well protected, but not all of them wrapped.
这样的包装真是懒惰
Such laziness, this packaging.
它们被来自布宜诺斯艾利斯的报纸包裹着
They were wrapped in newspapers from Buenos Aires.
奇怪的是，和那个小队一起送来的
And curiously enough, sent with that flotilla,
报纸的日期比我包裹我玻璃杯的报纸日期还要早
were newspapers dated back further than the newspapers wrapped around my glasses.
包裹我玻璃杯上的报纸新闻比这里报纸刊登的新闻还要多
My glasses carried more recent news than the papers distributed here.
是不是很吸引人？
Isn't that charming?
还是很感伤？
And sad?
这对你不重要，迭戈先生，因为我听说你随时都有可能被调走
It doesn't weigh on you, don Diego, because you'll be transferred any day now, I hear.
你希望被派遣到哪里？
Where are you hoping to be sent?
莱尔马
To the city of Lerma.
但不会是现在
But not just yet.
我们这里几乎没有优雅的场所
We have almost no occasion for elegance here.
报纸谈到了一部剧引起的轰动...
The newspapers spoke of the uproar caused by...
我忘记名字了
I forget the play.
掌声雷动...
The applause...
多么难得的场合，各种喝彩和掌声
How rare, the occasions for applause.
敬那些敢于伪装自己的演员们！
To the actors who dare to disguise themselves!
我们的朋友似乎感觉不太好
Our friend is not well.
- 要我派人去请帕洛斯医生吗？ - 不用了，我早知道会这样了
- Should I send for Doctor Palos? - No, I'm already aware.
迭戈...
Diego...
这对我来说是多么及时，去为你朋友的事情求情
How timely it is for me to intercede in favor of your friend's affairs.
卢西亚娜
Luciana.
请进！
Come in!
他走了吗？
Has he left?
他感到不舒服
He felt indisposed.
那么原谅他的粗鲁无礼了
His poor manners are forgiven.
- 你应该叫帕洛斯医生来看看 - 我会的
- You should send for Doctor Palos. - Of course.
等你朋友一康复，一定要再来我这，迭戈
As soon as your friend recovers, come see me again, Diego.
我会尽我所能
I'll do everything in my powers.
我会给我丈夫寄一封信
I'll send a letter to my husband,
告诉他我们的事情
informing him of our affairs.
当他离开时，他用温柔的信件折磨着我
When he's away, he torments me with tender missives.
那个黑仆
This servant here, this black,
送来往信件的，而且还是在这种大热天下...
comes and goes with messages. With this heat...
夫人
Señora,
得知这件事让我很难过
it grieves me to learn this.
许多女人轻视我的独守空房
Many women despise my independence.
而又有许多男人歪曲我的举止
And too many men misunderstand my conduct.
眼光狭小的人们
Small-minded people.
然而丰盈
Yet abundant.
在这样的大城市里
People are less alone
人们并不都是孤独的，而又相知甚少，你不觉得吗？
in the big cities, while knowing each other less, don't you think?
是这个夏天太糟糕了，或只是我不耐烦了？
Is this summer worse, or am I just more impatient?
房子使我窒息
Houses suffocate me.
我更喜欢河流
I prefer the river.
要是我们有几个寒冷的月份就好了
If only we had some cold months.
是的，没有冬天的话，感觉时间就没有过去
Yes, time doesn't pass when there's no winter.
雪...
The snow...
如此优雅
So elegant.
俄国公主裹着裘皮
The Russian princesses wrapped in furs.
喷着香水
The perfumes.
还有那铺着地毯而又暖和的房子
The heated houses, with rugs.
欧洲永远总是被那些从未拥有过的人铭记
Europe is best remembered by those who were never there.
而我对这些一无所知
I recall nothing about it.
婚姻迫使你忘记
Marriage forces you to forget.
又或者我曾被告知过
Or so I've been told.
迭戈，我们不要鲁莽行事
Diego, let's not be reckless.
- 总督派我来帮助你 - 这场闹剧是怎么回事？
- The Governor has sent me to assist you. - What's this circus?
这些人上面有人
These people have friends in high places.
- 总督想保住他的位子 - 那我的位子呢？
- The Governor wants to hold onto his position. - My position?
好吧，你也一样
Yes. Yours, too.
治安法官，迭戈·德·扎马
The Administration's Magistrate, Diego de Zama.
文图拉·普列托，治安法官助理
Ventura Prieto, Assistant Magistrate.
我们是康涅狄格州的老移民
We are old settlers of Concepción.
第一批来者的后代
Descendants of the first-comers.
我们的父亲是伊腊拉多明戈市的
Our father is a direct, blood descendant
一个直系血统的继承人
of don Domingo Martínez de Irala.
我们从这些土地上追赶印第安人
We chased the Indians from these lands.
但他们带着主张回来了
But they came back with claims.
我们又一次追赶他们
We chased them out again,
诸如此类
and so on.
他们逃到丛林里去了
They fled into the jungle.
我们去找他们
We went looking for them,
决不留情
and showed no mercy.
无人幸免，而现在没有人留下来工作
None were spared. And now there's no one left to work.
我只有我的孙女
I only have my granddaughter.
她浑身是血
She has mixed blood.
她被俘虏了
She was held captive.
我们设法把她弄回来了
We managed to get her back.
我们有权利要求赔偿
It's our right to claim an encomienda.
四十个被驯服的印第安人
Forty tame Indians.
印第安人有让步吗？
A concession of Indians?
你会有足够的印第安人的
You shall have enough Indians.
你不会受到任何伤害
You may return in peace.
你有总督的话：陛下会接受你的请求
You have the Governor's word: His Majesty will receive your request.
他们没有头衔或文件，我们什么都没有
They don't have title deeds or documents. We have nothing.
找个方法来取回它们，这个贵族家庭已经受够了
Find a way to retrieve them. This noble family has suffered enough.
伊腊拉家族不足以奴役当地人
The name of Irala isn't enough to enslave natives.
你说什么？文图拉
What did you say, Ventura?
拿走自由需要的不仅仅是一张有写有伊腊拉名字的纸
Taking away freedom requires more than a paper with Irala's name on it.
你是不同意我的善举吗？
You disapprove of my benevolence?
你认为什么样的称谓才能拥有获得印第安人的恩赐？
What title do you deem valid to obtain an encomienda of Indians?
一个也没有
None.
我是在和王室的工职人员谈说话吗？
Am I talking to a functionary of the Crown?
你是在和一个
You're talking to a man
惊讶于想要被误认为是西班牙人的美国人的数量
astonished by the number of Americans who want to pass for Spaniards
而不是他们本该是什么的人说话
instead of being what they are.
“一个惊讶于...”
"A man, astonished by..."
真是勇敢！
Such bravura!
他们说你差点俘获了维库尼亚·波尔图！
They say you almost captured Vicuña Porto!
迭戈
Diego,
他们对你做了什么？
what have they done to you?
你什么时候回来？
When will you return?
你们孩子们正在长大
Your children are growing.
他们厌倦了
They're growing tired.
我也一样
And so am I.
我会很快回去的，马尔塔
I'll be there soon, Marta.
有艘船来了
A ship is coming.
带着王室信件
With Royal Mail.
至于逾期的付款
For overdue payments.
我们必须要有耐心，马尔塔
We must be patient, Marta.
你受伤了吗？
Are you hurt?
他侮辱了我
He humiliated me.
他咬我
He bit me.
咬了很多次
So many times.
你替我报仇了吗？迭戈
Have you avenged me, Diego?
他强迫我顺从他的欲望，他嘲弄我
He forced me to submit to his desires. He mocked me.
你要为我报仇
You avenged me.
谁做的这些？丽塔
Who did this, Rita?
贝尔德兹长官
Officer Bermúdez.
秃顶那个？
The bald one?
他认为没有人愿意为我辩护
He thought no one would come to my defense.
你，扎马，一无所有
You, Zama, who have nothing.
我是不会让我父亲去参与一场斗争
I won't let my father fight a duel.
你没有什么可失去的
You have nothing to lose.
你要为我报仇
You avenged me.
而现在...
And now...
那个坏蛋死了
that scoundrel is dead.
不
No.
我没有杀他
I didn't kill him.
谁说的？
Who said that?
那你必须为我报仇
Then you must avenge me.
你有杀戮的能力，你没有什么可失去的
You're capable of killing, you have nothing to lose.
不，我有
Yes, I do.
我有妻子
A wife.
我还有孩子，丽塔
I have children, Rita.
我是王室的治安法官，是个公务员
I'm the Crown's magistrate. A functionary.
一个修道士来了
A monk has come.
他说你应该为丧葬费买单
He said you should pay for the funeral expenses.
谁死了？丽塔
Who died, Rita?
必须提前支付一部分
A part of the payment must be advanced.
当然，其余的可以在哀悼期允许的情况下支付
The rest can be paid when the mourning period allows, of course.
有人告诉我，死者的货物在海关被扣留了
I was told the cargo of the deceased is being held up at customs.
他们扣押了吗？
Have they seized it?
他们拿走了两个桶来支付丧葬费用
They released two casks to cover burial expenses.
我们出售白兰地的价格是非常合理的
Brandy that we sell at a very reasonable price.
人们已经厌倦了杜松子酒...
People grow tired of schnapps...
其他的桶被扣押了
The other casks were taken into custody.
海关官员告知我的
The customs officer informed me.
死神对于我们所有人来说都是有强加条件的
Death imposes conditions on all of us.
如果我为穷人举行葬礼，我会冒犯了他的声望
I'll offend his stature if I conduct a ceremony for the poor.
放哪？
Where?
他父亲旁边
Next to his father.
这些尸体的制备费用必须在转移到蒙得维的亚之前支付
The preparation of the bodies must be paid for before their transfer to Montevideo.
在那之前，我们必须把它们放在我们的地窖里
Until then, we'll have to keep them in our crypt.
这里温度比较低
It's cooler here.
我们也可以烧掉它们
We could also burn them.
他们死于瘟疫
They died of the plague.
阁下，不要招致更多的开支
Don't incur further expenses, Excellency.
这需要和负责帐目的主管会计师讨论下
That needs to be discussed with the Father Accountant in charge of accounts.
我想要刮胡子
I would like to shave.
我不想让你听到别人不幸的事
I didn't want you to hear about the unfortunate event from anyone else.
我们的朋友，奥连特尔人，已经死了
Our friend, the Oriental, is dead.
别扇了
I don't need air.
你的朋友身体也不是很好
Your friend wasn't well.
一个死去的男孩？
A dead boy?
船只上的瘟疫是无情的
The plague in the ships is relentless.
真是不幸啊！
How unfortunate.
玛伦巴想要结婚
Malemba wants to get married.
谁是玛伦巴？
Who is Malemba?
葬礼会使我们这些日子都很忙，我们必须为哀悼做准备
The funeral will keep us very busy these days. We must prepare for the mourning.
让我们为他的荣誉干杯吧
Let's drink in his honor.
不会有人守灵的
There won't be a wake.
奥连特尔人是个严肃的人
The Oriental was an austere man.
主教认为我们应该按他的方式来
The Bishop believes we should adhere to his ways.
真是朴素
Such austerity.
可惜了
What a pity.
不会有人守灵的，只有一些谦虚和无聊的东西
There will be no wake. Only something modest and boring.
多么悲哀，真遗憾啊
How sad. What a shame.
谁想要结婚？
Who wants to get married?
玛伦巴
Malemba.
她赎回了她的自由，但又想要失去它
She bought her freedom and already wants to lose it.
我告诉我丈夫：她不能准许
I told my husband: she can't give her consent.
一个哑巴能给与出她的准许吗？
Can a mute give her consent?
不能！
No!
黑仆今天送来了信件
The black came today with letters.
人人都在觊觎我的身体
All men covet my body.
荷奴里奥，我的丈夫，被肉欲迷住了
Honorio, my own husband, is fascinated by flesh.
我鄙视他
I despise him.
和那些渴望拥有一切的人
And all men for their desire to possess.
我很感激
I'm grateful
因为遇见了一个你这样有个性的女人
for having met a woman of your character.
玛伦巴受的苦够多了
Malemba has suffered enough.
她游过了河，逃离了一个虐待狂的烟农
She swam across the river, fleeing an abusive tobacco farmer.
她游了好几个小时，多长时间来着？
She swam not only for hours. How long was it?
游了多久？
How long?
一整天都待在水中，紧紧的握住她的生命，然而她还是在查科被抓了
Days in the water, holding on to her life. She was captured again in Chaco.
他们剥了她的脚皮
They skinned her feet,
把那可怕的植物揉搓在她身上
and rubbed that horrible plant on her.
还有她的脚底上
On the soles of her feet.
我以为她的哑巴和跛行是联系在一起的
I thought her muteness and limping were linked.
但她不是哑巴
She's not mute.
她有舌头
She has her tongue.
我想解决这桩婚事
I want to settle this marriage affair.
玛伦巴的婚事
Malemba's.
没有什么能阻止它
Nothing prevents it.
有效同意书需以书面形式给出
Valid consent is given in written form.
你丈夫的签字并会使婚姻具有合法性
Your husband's signature will validate the union.
你的哑巴可以结婚
Your mute can get married.
你应得一个吻
You deserve a kiss.
但不是现在
Not now.
给迭戈·德·扎马的消息
A message for Diego de Zama.
我就是，请说
It's me. Speak.
总督说你得走了
The Governor says you must go.
我得走了？
I must go?
去他的办公室
To his office.
消息已传达
Mail has arrived.
搞定了！
It's over!！
总督？
Governor?
“请求在听证会上遵守这项主权条款
"Having requested observance of this sovereign provision
并在本案中听取王室协议
and given a hearing to the Royal Accord on this case,
我已经通过去年11月27日的这项法令解决了此案
I have resolved by this decree of last November 27th,
正如我宣布的声明，吧啦吧啦吧啦...”
declaring as I declare, that blah, blah, blah..."
我要被调到西班牙去了
I'm being transferred to Spain.
王室信件？
Royal Mail?
什么时候到的？有给我的消息吗？
When did it arrive? Any news for me?
没有，暂时没有
No, not yet.
由于你的较高官衔，我被迫驱逐了文图拉·普列托
I've been forced, due to your superior rank, to deport Ventura Prieto.
因为争吵而驱逐？
Deported for a brawl?
那只是一场争吵
It was just a brawl.
街头争吵对你的地位很不利
A street brawl doesn't look good for a functionary of your status.
我不想过分的苛刻
I didn't want to be excessively severe.
我给文图拉·普列托写了一封推荐信
I've written a recommendation letter for Ventura Prieto.
重要的是他的名誉不会受到玷污
What's important is that his reputation not be tainted.
文图拉是西班牙的公务员
Ventura is a Spanish functionary.
你负担不起这样的风险，迭戈
You can't afford such risks, Diego.
你已经选择了莱尔马
You've chosen the city of Lerma.
是的
Yes.
我已要求调到莱尔马
I've requested a transfer to the city of Lerma.
文图拉·普列托也选择了莱尔马
Ventura Prieto has chosen the city of Lerma.
被驱逐出境的...
The deported...
可以选择他的目的地
gets to choose his destination
并得到推荐？
and gets a recommendation?
把王室的决议抄录一份
Make a copy of the Crown's resolution.
并立即宣布我即将起程
And announce my departure at once.
玛伦巴
Malemba,
告诉夫人我需要见她
tell your Señora I need to see her.
玛伦巴，有人在门口吗？
Malemba, is someone at the door?
你不打算通知一声吗？
Will you not announce me?
荷奴里奥已经睡了一阵子，突然我惊醒了，看见了它
Honorio had been asleep for a while when suddenly I woke up startled and saw it,
它爬上了荷奴里奥的脖子
crawling up Honorio's neck.
我无法动弹、哭泣或呼喊
I couldn't move, cry or shout.
这是什么？
What's here?
很痒
It itches.
黎明时分，我在地上看到了它，它还在移动，背上有蛆
At dawn, I saw it on the ground. It was still moving, with grubs on its back.
它是蛛蜂
It was the spider wasp.
它在活蜘蛛体内产卵
It lays eggs inside living spiders.
帮我一下
Help me with this.
玛伦巴，有人在门口吗？
Malemba, is someone at the door?
大马士革的窗帘
Curtains from Damascus.
丢失
Missing.
有乌木钉的桌子
A table with ebony nailing.
那墙上本有一幅画
There was a painting on that wall.
国王陛下的肖像
A portrait of Our Majesty, the King.
总督也非常喜欢那幅画
The Governor was very fond of that painting, too.
天鹅绒沙发的椅子呢？
The chairs with velvet upholstery?
他也是很喜欢
They were to his liking, too.
他拿着马具和14个马鞍
He took the harnesses and 14 saddles.
我应该记录下这些吗？
Should I record this?
不是他
That's not him.
是那个
It's that one.
他不能走吗？
Can't he walk?
他能说话吗？
Does he talk?
会几个词
A few words.
“当有很多鱼的时候，水手的妻子会变得富有！”
"The sailor's wife gets rich, when plenty are the fish!"
来，扎马，拉把椅子过来
Come, Zama. Pull up a chair.
今天是个幸运日
Today is a lucky day.
给他看看耳朵
Show him the ears.
告诉他那个故事
Tell him the story.
这耳朵是维库尼亚·波尔图的
The ears of Vicuña Porto,
在处决前被切了下来
cut off before his execution.
残忍的人啊...
The cruelty of men...
这就是个岌岌可危的问题
This is what's at stake.
轻点
Slowly.
总督，我给你带来了一个抄写员
Governor, I've brought you a scribe.
如果这场游戏能持续很长时间的话，我会让他走的
If this game will last for long, I can excuse him.
抄写员？
A scribe?
为你所提出的事写信
For the letter you offered to write.
写什么信？
What letter?
在我成为父亲的时，我向国王提出过的请求
My request to the King on the occasion of my becoming a father.
你是个父亲？
You're a father?
把孩子带来，他们能带来好运
Bring the child, they bring luck.
耳朵易手！
The ears change hands!
包里有什么？
What's in the bag?
让我来
Allow me.
好极了，好极了！
Well, well!
治安法官
Magistrate.
这个...毫无价值
This... is worthless.
椰子毫无价值，对吧？
Coconuts are worthless, right?
没关系
Doesn't matter.
不管怎样，我还是会留着它
I'll keep it anyway.
警员
Officer,
把我们的朋友送到城门去
see our friend to the city gates.
维库尼亚·波尔图已经死了
Vicuña Porto is dead.
没有人可以碰它们
One shouldn't touch them.
别碰
Don't touch.
不
No.
这耳朵是维库尼亚·波尔图的
The ears of Vicuña Porto.
维库尼亚...
Vicuña...
...已经死了
...is dead.
这耳朵是维库尼亚·波尔图的
The ears of Vicuña Porto.
总督
Governor,
你能处理一下那封信吗？
could you attend to the letter?
当然可以
Of course.
给国王的一封要求你调动的信
A letter to the King requesting your transfer.
我们会为我的好朋友向陛下恳求的
We'll plead to His Majesty for my good friend.
你在写什么？
What are you writing?
一本书，总督
A book, Governor.
我们需要起草一封信，然后...
We need to draft a letter to be sealed and...
一本书？
A book?
要造孩子
Make children,
而不是写书
not books.
从我们的治安法官曼努埃尔那里吸取教训
Learn a lesson from our Magistrate, Manuel.
我不知道我的孩子会怎样
I can't know how my children will be.
但我知道这本书该怎么写
But I do know how this book will be.
阁下，我相信没什么好担心的
Your Eminence, I believe there's nothing to worry about.
走起来
Let's go.
- 我应该再找一个抄写员吗？ - 走起来！
- Should I look for another scribe? - Let's go!
我应该再找一个抄写员吗？
Should I look for another scribe?
为什么要在政府办公区里写一本书
Why write a book inside the house of Government,
而其他人都在为陛下的荣耀而工作？
while others work for the glory of His Majesty?
我只是希望...
I only wish...
你知道这本书吗？
Were you aware of this book?
阁下，我相信没什么好担心的
Your Eminence, I believe there's nothing to worry about.
你不知道这本书吗？
You didn't know about this book?
我从没听说过这本书
I never knew about the book.
扎马，你来这儿多久了？你对此一无所知吗？
How long have you been here, Zama? You knew nothing about it?
政府中最老的官员也对这本书一无所知？
The oldest functionary in the Administration knows nothing about this book?
我想用他们的头烤这些鱼
I want to grill those fish with their heads.
把马赶出去，这不是马厩
Get the horses out of here. This isn't a stable.
- 怎么了？ - 给迭戈·德·扎马的消息
- What is it? - A message for Diego de Zama.
- 我就是，怎么了？ - 财产清单
- That's me. What is it? - Inventory.
什么财产清单？
What inventory?
他们把所有的东西都搬到院子里去了
They're taking everything to the patio.
总督命令每个人都要清洁整理
The Governor commands everyone to clean and tidy up.
拿着这个
Take this.
我知道总督要你来就我的书作报告
I know the Governor has requested you report on my book.
这就是
Here it is.
供您考虑
For your consideration.
费尔南德斯
Fernández,
我还没有决定我的新住所
I haven't yet decided on my new residence.
我的家具还需放在教堂里一段时间
I need to keep my furniture in the chapel a bit longer.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
你是我的第一个读者
You're my first reader.
哪些是你的东西？
Which are your things?
那张床
The bed.
这三把椅子
These three chairs.
两个写着我名字的小箱子
Two small chests with my name on them.
他们正在清点政府的财产
They're making an inventory of the Government's property.
你的家具已经被登记了
Your furniture has been listed.
我可以去掉些东西
I could remove some things.
但它是有代价的
But it has a cost.
真是办事不力！
How inadequate!
当我在新的住所定居后
When I've settled in a new residence,
我会派人来拿我的东西的
I'll send for my belongings.
我们现在必须尽最大的努力去做这件事
We must do it now, and with the utmost discretion.
有人告诉我郊区有家旅店可以住
I was told of an inn on the outskirts.
让我帮你
Let me help you.
你是我的第一个读者
You're my first reader.
搬的时候小心点
Take care of the move.
她抱着的那个男孩是我儿子
That boy she's holding is my son.
- 那是他的母亲吗？ - 是的
- Is that the mother? - Yes.
就那个
That one.
艾米莉亚
Emilia.
费尔南德斯
Fernández,
把那张床搬给艾米莉亚夫人
take that bed to Señora Emilia.
这个垃圾场是怎么回事？
What is this dump?
搬运工
The porters,
他们害怕这所房子
they're afraid of this house.
把它放在那
Leave it there.
我只呆几天
I'll only stay a few days.
直到我找到合适的住所
Until I find a proper residence.
把这本书保存起来，直到你完成报告为止
Keep the book until you finish it.
我还没有制作一个副本
I haven't made a copy.
我对你的书一无所知
I know nothing about your book.
我从来不知道它存在，而且没有人要求我报告
I never knew it existed. And no one has requested a report.
总督认为政府的办公时间应是在为国王服务
The Governor feels that working hours at the Government House are to serve the King.
大人
Your Grace,
恕我直言
with all due respect,
当我写书的时候，我没有老师
I have no master, when I write my book.
我希望它是无法解释的现象
I wish it were the inexplicable.
但是，有一个男孩在里面
But a boy is in there.
埋了这本书
Bury this book,
直到这一切结束，费尔南德斯
until all of this blows over, Fernández.
走开！
Go away!
你是谁？
Who are you?
祖马拉
Zumala.
给我一条链子和一把锁
Bring me a chain and a lock.
没有人可以进入这所房子
No one enters this house.
告诉旅店老板给我拿一条链子和一把锁来
Tell the innkeeper to bring me a chain and a lock.
他病了
He's sick.
旅店老板生病了
The innkeeper is sick.
我需要一件衬衣
I need a shirt.
我是你的妻子吗？
Am I your wife?
你是我儿子的母亲
You're the mother of my son.
总督，我应该为你给国王写的提议
Governor, should I fetch another scribe
再找个抄写员吗？
for the letter to the King that you suggested?
没有报告就没有信
No letter without a report.
什么报告？
What report?
需要我自己去要吗？
Do I need to ask for it?
一本背着王室写的书，也就是背着你写的书
A book is being written behind the Crown's back, which is your back as well.
阁下，我想您不必担心
Your Eminence, I don't think you should worry.
你应该担心
You should worry.
我需要一份残酷的报告
I expect a damning report, ruthless,
无情地结束这场骗局
that puts an end to this chicanery.
只有这样，我才愿意向国王提出你的要求
Only then will I be willing to make your request to the King.
当然，你的儿子是个私生子
Leaving out, of course, that your son is a bastard.
身为治安法官应该很清楚
The Magistrate knows well
这种好处只会留给公务员的合法儿子
that this benefit is only reserved for a functionary's legitimate son.
总督
Governor,
我的调动已经在可容忍的时间内延误很久了
my transfer has suffered more delays than those tolerable.
这是我的想法：
Here's what I think:
你想要离开？
You want to leave?
那就写报告
Write the report.
他有他自己的方式
He has his ways.
他们说他无缘无故地处死了维库尼亚
They say he executed Vicuña without mercy.
祖马拉！
Zumala!
祖马拉...
Zumala...
我敲了铃，但没有人回答
I rang the bell and nobody answered.
我想吃点东西
I'd like to eat.
我们都很难过
We were sad.
她死了
She died.
谁死了？
Who died?
祖马拉已经死了
Zumala is dead.
那你是谁？
Then who are you?
托拉
Tora.
Tora,
你应该把我介绍给其他客人...
you should introduce me to the other guests...
- 那位留着头发的女士... - 你是唯一一位客人，扎马
- the ladies with the hair... - You are our only guest, Zama.
治安法官...
Magistrate...
总督下令重新整理
The Governor ordered this rearrangement.
听候吩咐
At your service.
这些天很少
These are days of scarce work
为我的职位效劳了
for my Ministry.
我听说了
I've been informed of that.
总督提到报告了吗？
Did the Governor mention the report?
什么报告？
What report?
你知道的
You were told about it.
没有
No.
总督只叫我搬到这里来
The Governor only told me to relocate here.
这里！
Here!
这是给我的
That's for me.
艾米莉亚女士给的鱼
These are doña Emilia's fish.
艾米莉亚女士送的礼物？
Gifts from doña Emilia?
它们是买来的
They were bought.
不是礼物
Not gifts.
逾期的付款
Overdue payments.
29乘1000等于29000
减3500等于...
Minus 3,500 already received, makes...
这房子是腐烂透了
This house is rotten.
休息吧，迭戈先生
Rest, don Diego.
密封的信件才是最重要的，费尔南德斯
The sealed letter is the one that counts, Fernández.
穿越海洋去提出申诉...
Crossing the ocean to make a plea...
慢点来
Take it easy.
有点烫
It's hot.
在晚上
At night,
我们可以听到很大的噪音
we could hear a great noise.
然后它们就出现了
Then they appeared.
它们是...
They're...
圆形的岩石
round rocks,
像椰子一样
like coconuts,
但却是用石头做的
but made of stone.
它们的内心都充满了珍贵的宝石
And their insides are filled with precious stones.
太漂亮了...
So pretty...
多么神奇啊！
What marvels!
我不想玷污费尔南德斯的名誉
I wouldn't want to tarnish Fernández's honor.
也许应送他去莱尔马
Maybe send him to the city of Lerma,
带着推荐信
with a recommendation.
他还年轻
He's very young.
一段小句应该足够警告了
A minor sentence should be enough warning.
写得好极了
Excellent.
残酷无情
Ruthless.
像是...
Such a...
一只锋利的笔
sharp pen.
阁下能写
Could Your Excellency write
那封你为我的信吗？
that letter you offered me?
什么信？
What letter?
写给国王的
The letter to the King,
请求我的调动
requesting my transfer.
当然，你现在是个父亲了
Of course. You're a father now.
第一封信很重要
The first letter is very important.
第一封信是什么意思？
What do you mean, the first letter?
一两年后，我们将寄出第二封
In a year or two, we'll send the second one.
陛下直到收到第二封才会考虑这些问题
His Majesty doesn't consider these matters until the second time.
我马上给你发第一封信
I'll immediately send the first letter.
我会给你发第一封信的，马上
I'll send the first letter, immediately.
迭戈·德·扎马先生
Don Diego de Zama.
谢谢你来
Thank you for coming.
你的头衔令人印象深刻
The list of your titles is impressive.
你是一个“行政首长”
You were a "corregidor".
能找到这样一个任务的志愿者是真是令人惊讶
It's surprising to find a volunteer for a mission like this.
帕里利亚上尉
Captain Parrilla
部队指挥
is commanding the troops.
你清楚任务吗？
Are you aware of the mission?
我们必须除掉维库尼亚·波尔图
We must get rid of Vicuña Porto.
他们打不过我们的，上尉
They won't beat us, Captain.
我们寻求的是恢复商业
What we seek is to reactivate commerce.
我们必须杜绝偷窃
We must put an end to theft,
纵火
to arson,
赌场
to gambling houses.
我们必须整顿贸易路线
We must clean up the trade routes.
这就是我的政府所要达到的目标
That is what my Administration sets out to achieve.
你来这里多久了？
How long have you been here?
有一阵子了
A long time now.
好极了
Excellent.
我们有你的调动申请
We have your transfer request here.
陛下将庆祝这回战事，特别是取得了胜利后
His Majesty will celebrate this return to arms and especially to victory.
我们必须把维库尼亚·波尔图的头带回来
We must bring back the head of Vicuña Porto.
你会受到英雄般的欢迎
You'll be received as heroes.
为你举行盛大的仪式
With great pomp.
我昨晚醒来，发现有东西在我脖子上爬
I woke up last night and felt something crawling on my neck.
我这样弄了一下
I went like this,
然后感到有些奇怪
and felt something strange.
它在肿胀
It's swollen.
该是蛛蜂
Must be a spider wasp.
不对，是蜘蛛
No. A spider.
是印第安人吗？
Is it an Indian?
如果是的话，就会有银器
If so, there'll be pieces of silver.
是个死人
It's a dead man.
印第安人的独木舟和其他两个被遗弃的东西
The Indians, the canoeist and the other two deserted.
没银器？
No silver?
什么也没有，只有死人
Nothing, only a dead man.
带些人去抓逃兵！
Take some men and capture the deserters!
别动，安静点
Don't move. Be still.
有500人或更多
他们是瞎子
They're the blind.
保持冷静，你就会活下去的
Stay calm and you'll live.
他们受到了惩罚
They were punished.
孩子们是在惩罚后出生的
And the children were born after the punishment.
维库尼亚·波尔图给的惩罚吗？
Punished by Vicuña Porto?
也许是你们这些人给的
Maybe by you people.
他们带走了马
They took the horses.
对于瞎子来说他们走得很快啊
They walk fast for blind people.
他们走得很快，是为了不让孩子们失望
They walk fast so as not to disappoint their children.
夜晚对瞎子来说更安全
Nighttime is safer for the blind.
我宁愿在白天躲起来
I rather hide during the day.
那是我的剑
That's my sword.
我应该自我介绍一下
I should introduce myself.
我的名字是维库尼亚·波尔图
My name is Vicuña Porto.
你是？
And you?
“行政首长”的名字是什么？
What's the “corregidor”'s name?
请仁慈点
Mercy.
你说什么？“行政首长”
What did you say, “corregidor”?
- 谁在哪？ - 迭戈·德·扎马
- Who's there? - Diego de Zama.
我们就过来了
We're coming.
他们带走了马
They took the horses.
什么都没有留下
There's nothing left.
只要不说出我的名字你就会活下去
Don't say my name and you'll live.
停下！
Halt!
有两个人正在靠近，别转身！
Two Guanáes are coming, don't turn around!
别转身
Don't turn around.
他们是幻想
They're fantasized.
“幻想？”
"Fantasized?"
伪装者
Disguised.
朋友
Friends.
别动
Stay still.
他们邀请我们去庆祝会
They invited us to a celebration.
庆祝会？
A celebration?
告诉他们，西班牙国王，这些广大土地的领主
Tell them that the King of Spain, Lord of these vast lands,
向他问好，表示他的友好
sends his regards and offers His friendship.
他们想要动物
They want the animal.
“行政首长”有什么建议吗？
Does the "corregidor" have any suggestions?
走吧
Let's go.
迭戈·德·扎马
Diego de Zama.
士兵加斯珀·托莱多
Soldier Gaspar Toledo.
士兵吉塞佩斯·纳西门托
Soldier Giusepe Nascimento.
士兵安比力诺·马瑞亚
Soldier Umbilino Maria.
没有维库尼亚·波尔图我们不能回去
We can't return without Vicuña Porto.
看见那个拿着刀的人了吗？
See that man with the knife?
那就是维库尼亚·波尔图
That's Vicuña Porto.
叛徒
Traitor.
小心！
Careful!
正中红心
Right in the middle.
食物！
Food!
我们有吃的了，上尉！
We have food, Captain!
- 今日吃鱼！ - 饥荒结束了！
- Fish today! - The famine is over!
食物！
Food!
维库尼亚·波尔图！
Vicuña Porto!
告诉你的人排队放下武器
Tell your men to line up and lay down their arms.
都结束了
It's over.
叛徒！
Traitor!
气味
That smell.
老虎会闻到那只手臂的气味
The tigers will smell that arm.
死肉会使它们好奇
Dead meat makes them curious.
但它们并不会吃
But they won't eat it.
相反，它们会攻击我们
Instead, they'll pounce us.
别告诉他们我病了
Don't tell them I'm sick.
叛徒
Traitor.
谁在唱歌？
Who's singing?
Who sings?
我犯了罪
I've committed sins.
但不是所有这些...
But not all those...
他们都怪罪于维库尼亚·波尔图
they blame on Vicuña Porto.
明白吗？
Understand?
这就对了
That's right.
他们说的维库尼亚·波尔图根本不存在
The Vicuña Porto they talk about doesn't exist.
那不是我
It's not me.
谁也不是
It's no one.
只是个名字
It's a name.
一个名字而已
A name.
明白吗？
Understand?
我的名字是加斯珀·托莱多
My name is Gaspar Toledo.
这是怎么一回事?
What is it?
我叫什么？“行政首长”
What's my name, "corregidor"?
我不是“行政首长”
I'm not a "corregidor".
这就对了
That's right.
你不是那个“行政首长”
You're not the "corregidor",
我也不是维库尼亚·波尔图
and I'm not Vicuña Porto.
但是...
But...
我的手下想要发财
my men want to get rich.
我的手下
My men
想要发财
want to be rich.
我答应他们会发财的
I promised them it would be so.
我需要“行政首长”
I need the "corregidor"
去找到椰子
to find the coconuts.
什么椰子？
What coconuts?
你是那个“行政首长”，对吗？
You are the "corregidor", right?
给点水吧！
A little water!
- 上尉想要水？ - 水！
- The captain wants water? - Water!
别看着我，叛徒，连一瞥都别想
Don't look at me, traitor. Not even a glance.
水
Water.
我有一个计划，陛下会奖赏你的
I have a plan. His Majesty will reward you.
我们会带着荣耀回去...
We'll return with honors...
他们想要发财
They want to get rich.
你说个地方
Name the place.
北方的任何地方，任何地方都可以
Anywhere North, any place will do.
什么地方？
What place?
椰子在的地方！
Where the coconuts are!
什么椰子？
What coconuts?
你是“行政首长”
You're the "corregidor".
“行政首长”
"Corregidor",
有石头的地方，圆形的石头的地方
the place with the stones, the round stones.
向导不知道这个地方吗？
The guide doesn't know the place?
我没有向导
I'm not a guide.
“行政首长”知道那个地方
The "corregidor" knows the place.
椰子，里面尽是宝石
The coconuts, full of precious stones.
“行政首长”知道...
The "corregidor" knows...
那些宝石头毫无价值
Those stones are worthless.
他在说谎！
He's lying!
它们毫无价值
They're worthless.
叛徒
Traitor.
它们毫无价值
They're worthless.
他在说谎！
He's lying!
椰子在哪里？
Where are the coconuts?
那些石头毫无价值
Those stones are worthless.
石头！
The stones!
他在说谎！
You're lying!
你会死的！
You'll die!
死神降临到扎马身上！
Death to Zama!
死神！
Death!
快走！
Leave!
我为你做的事从没人为我做过
I do for you what no one did for me.
他要死了
He's lying.
快走！
Leave!
我对你的欲望说不
I say no to your hopes.
死神降临到扎马身上！
Death to Zama!
抓住他
Hold him.
把你的残肢埋到沙子里去
Shove your stumps in the sand.
如果你停止流血了，你就会活下来
If you don't bleed out, you'll survive.
你想活下去吗？
Do you want to live?